Guide to the Chapel Reference Collection, 1933-ongoing
Duke University. University Archives
Chapel Reference collection 1933-ongoing
Duke University. University Archives
2.1 linear feet Extent: 2250 Items
UA.01.11.0049
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Chapel Reference Collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research.
Historical Note
History from the Duke Chapel website http://www.chapel.duke.edu/building/history.html
When James B. Duke selected the site for Duke University's West Campus, in 1925, he chose to locate the Chapel on the site's highest ridge. The Chapel was the first building planned for the new campus, but the last one to be completed. Construction started in 1930, was completed in 1935, and cost nearly $2.3 million. The Chapel began to be used before its stained-glass windows and other details were finished; commencement was held in the Chapel in 1932.
Although the Chapel was inspired by other buildings, including English cathedrals and the chapels of other American universities, it is not a copy of any other specific building. The architect was Julian Abele, chief designer with the Horace Trumbauer firm, of Philadelphia. America's first black architect of renown, Abele was educated at the University of Pennsylvania and in France. In addition to Duke's original West Campus, he designed the Georgian buildings on Duke's East Campus. Abele's other designs include the Philadelphia Museum of Art, Harvard's Widener Library, and mansions for James B. Duke.
Collection Overview
The Chapel Reference Collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research. It includes subject files ordered alphabetically on various subjects relating to the Chapel. Some prominent subjects include: administrative history of the Chapel; the organs (Aeolian, Brombaugh, Flentrop); calendar of events; carillon; Chapel choir; sarcophagi; special services/events; weddings; and windows.
Subject Headings
Chapels -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University -- Buildings; Duke University. Chapel; Duke University. Chapel -- Organs
Related Material
Building Reference collection, 1972-2004.
University Archives, Duke University.
Chapel records, 1931-[ongoing].
University Archives, Duke University.
Chapel Sermons, 1954-1987 [sound recording]
University Archives, Duke University.
Facilities Management Department records, 1990-2006
University Archives, Duke University.
Friends of Duke Chapel Records, 1973 - 1999
University Archives, Duke University.
Minister to the University (Dean of the Chapel) records, 1940-1984
University Archives, Duke University.
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, 1933-ongoing, 4 Boxes
  - Acoustics and Duke Chapel/ Lawson, Dewey T. (Box 1)
  - Administration (Box 1)
  - Administrative Committee Minutes, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Committee Minutes, 1964-1973 (Box 1)
  - Advent Meditations (Box 1)
  - Aeolian Organ (Box 1)
  - Anecdotes (Box 1)
  - Architecture (Box 1)
  - Attendee Survey; Newspaper Articles re: Survey(s) (Box 1)
  - Baptism (Box 1)
  - Broadcast of Sunday Service, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures and Guides (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Brochures and Guides (duplicates) (Box 1)
  - Brombaugh Organ (Box 1)
  - Calendar of Events (Box 1)
  - Carillon (Box 1)
  - Carillon Recital Programs, 1932-1953 (Box 1)
  - Carillonneur (Box 1)
  - Carolina Arts Magazine: Winter 1981 (Box 1)
  - The Chapel A Great, Towering Church draft of introduction to photographic book on The Chapel by William H. Willimon ca. 1987 (Box 1)
  - Chapel Choir -- News Articles, Programs (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Chapel -- Children's Choir (Box 1)
  - Chapel Choir -- China Tour, 1997 Program Video in A.V. collection (Box 1)
  - Chapel Choir Reunion, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Chapel Choir Reunion, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Chapel Policies (Box 2)
  - Chorale, circa 1966-2001 (Box 2)
  - Christmas (Box 2)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - A Concert in Celebration of 1999 - The Year of Music in Duke Chapel (Box 2)
  - The Congregation at Duke Chapel (Box 2)
  - Construction Costs as of October 31, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Construction Projects (Box 2)
  - Crowther, Charles H. [Designer of Woodcarvings] (Box 2)
  - Deaths, suicides (Box 2)
  - Dedication Programs, June 2, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Development Campaign (Box 2)
  - Duke Chapel Heartbeat [newsletter] (Box 2)
  - Duke University Chapel, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
  - Duke University Church (Box 2)
  - 50th Anniversary Programs of the Laying of the Cornerstone (Box 2)
  - 50th Anniversary of Dedication of Chapel, June 9, 1985 (Box 2)
  - First Sunday Sermon (Box 2)
  - First Sunrise Service (Box 2)
  - Flentrop Organ (B.N. Duke Memorial) (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2)
    - News Articles (Box 2)
    - Dedication Programs (Box 2)
  - Friends of the Chapel (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee minutes, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters (Box 2)
      - Chapel Voices (Box 2)
      - View From the Chapel (Box 2)
  - Gifts to Chapel (Box 2)
  - Gotham, Elizabeth Lucina Memorial Fund (Box 2)
  - Guest Preachers. Duke Chapel, 1939-1944 (Box 2)
  - Hebrew Scrolls (Box 3)
  - History (Box 3)
  - Hostess Responsibilities (Box 3)
  - Interior (Box 3)
  - Lenten Meditations (Box 3)
  - The Mary Duke Biddle Organ - Dedication on April 27, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Memorial Services, 1936-2996 (13 folders) (Box 3)
  - Ministers (Box 3)
  - Miscellany (Box 3)
  - The Mission of the Chapel, by Bishop Kenneth Goodson (Box 3)
  - Music - Director Search, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Music - Original (Box 3)
  - Paintings, prints, etc. (Box 3)
  - Recitals, 1932-1933 (Box 3)
  - Replica of Chapel (Box 3)
  - Chapel - Sarcophagi (Box 3)
  - Sermons Index (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - June 1932-November 1973 (Box 3)
    - December 1973-July 2000 (Box 3)
  - Sound System (Box 3)
  - Special Events (Box 3)
    - Concerts and Lectures (Box 3)
    - Messiah Programs, 1933- (Box 3)
  - Special Services (Box 4)
    - General (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - V-E Day Observance; Speech and program (Box 4)
    - Rev. Robert Whitridge Estill (Box 4)
    - Services for Election Officials (Box 4)
  - Spire and Spirit, by Alice Phillips (Box 4)
  - Statistical Info. And Retention Schedule, 1935-1982 (Box 4)
  - Statues (Box 4)
  - Student Preachers (Box 4)
  - Sunday Concert Series -- Programs, 1971-1976 (Box 4)
  - Symbols (Box 4)
  - Tile (Box 4)
  - Tour of Chapel -- Self-guided (Box 4)
  - 20th Anniversary Celebration, June 1, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Visitor Statistics (Box 4)
  - Waldo Beach Hymn Competition (Box 4)
  - Weddings/Unions (Box 4)
    - General (Box 4)
    - Same Sex Unions -- statement from Dean and newspaper clipping re: Controversy, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Same Sex Unions, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Windows (Box 4)
    - General (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - The Windows of the Duke University Chapel, by Alice Phillips (c.3 and c. 4) (Box 4)
  - Woodcarving/Woodwork (Box 4)